ⓘ These English & Foreign subtitles created by ZoowlCZ (ver. 2024-10) are an expanded version of the English subtitles created by Bokutox of YIFY-TORRENTS (Torporr of Outland PVP (EU)).
ⓘ Very special thanks to Gwaith-i-Phethdain, Magpie of A Magpie's Nest and Friends, and Monoverantus
for their extraordinary work on deciphering the dialogs and lyrics.
ⓘ Special thanks also to TheGloriousLori and José Figueredo.
ⓘ For correct displaying of these subtitles, use a media player
supporting ASS tags in .srt files.
Smeagol!
I've got one!
I've got a fish, Smea... Smeagol!
Pull it in. Go on. Go on. Go on. Pull it in.
Deagol!
Deagol?
Deagol.
Give us that, Deagol, my love.
Why?
Because...
it's my birthday and I wants it.
My precious.
They cursed us.
Murderer.
"Murderer" they called us.
They cursed us and drove us away.
Gollum.
And we wept, precious.
We wept to be so alone.
- and cool
- So nice for feet
And we only wish To catch a fish
So juicy sweet
And we forgot the taste of bread...
the sound of trees...
the softness of the wind.
We even forgot our own name.
My precious.
Wake up!
Wake up, sleepies.
We must go, yes.
We must go at once.
Haven't you had any sleep, Mr. Frodo?
I've gone and had too much.
Must be getting late.
No.
It isn't.
It isn't midday yet.
The days are growing darker.
Come on!
Must go! No time!
Not before Mr. Frodo's had something to eat.
No time to lose, silly.
Here.
What about you?
Oh, no, I'm not hungry.
Leastways, not for lembas bread.
Sam.
All right.
We don't have that much left.
We have to be careful or we're going to run out.
You go ahead and eat that, Mr. Frodo.
I've rationed it.
There should be enough.
For what?
The journey home.
Come, Hobbitses.
Very close now.
Very close to Mordor.
No safe places here.
Hurry.
It's good.
Definitely from the Shire.
Longbottom Leaf.
I feel like I'm back at The Green Dragon.
- Green Dragon.
- A mug of ale in my hand.
Putting my feet up on a settle after a hard day's work.
Only, you've never done a hard day's work.
Welcome, my lords...
to Isengard!
You young rascals! A merry hunt you've led us on...
and now we find you feasting and... and smoking!
We are sitting on a field of victory...
enjoying a few well-earned comforts.
The salted pork is particularly good.
Salted pork?
- Hobbits.
- We're under orders from Treebeard...
who's taken over management of Isengard.
Young Master Gandalf.
I'm glad you've come.
Wood and water, stock and stone I can master.
But there is a wizard to manage here...
locked in his tower.
Show yourself.
Be careful.
Even in defeat, Saruman is dangerous.
Well, let's just have his head and be done with it.
No.
We need him alive.
We need him to talk.
You have fought many wars and
slain many men, Theoden King...
and made peace afterwards.
Can we not take counsel together
as we once did, my old friend?
Can we not have peace, you and I?
We shall have peace.
We shall have peace...
when you answer for the burning of the Westfold...
and the children that lie dead there!
We shall have peace when the lives of the soldiers...
whose bodies were hewn even as they lay dead...
against the gates of the Hornburg, are avenged!
When you hang from a gibbet for
the sport of your own crows...
we shall have peace.
Gibbets and crows?
Dotard!
What do you want, Gandalf Greyhame?
Let me guess. The Key of Orthanc.
Or perhaps the Keys of Barad-dur itself...
along with the crowns of the seven
kings and the rods of the Five Wizards!
Your treachery has already cost many lives.
Thousands more are now at risk.
But you could save them, Saruman.
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
So you have come here for information.
I have some for you.
Something festers in the heart of Middle-earth.
Something that you have failed to see.
But the Great Eye has seen it.
Even now he presses his advantage.
His attack will come soon.
You're all going to die.
But you know this, don't you, Gandalf?
You cannot think that this Ranger will
ever sit upon the throne of Gondor.
This exile, crept from the
shadows, will never be crowned king.
Gandalf does not hesitate to
sacrifice those closest to him...
those he professes to love.
Tell me, what words of comfort
did you give the Halfling...
before you sent him to his doom?
The path that you have set
him on can only lead to death.
I've heard enough!
Shoot him. Stick an arrow in his gob.
No.
Come down, Saruman...
- and your life will be spared.
- Save your pity and your mercy.
I have no use for it!
Saruman...
your staff is broken.
Grima, you need not follow him.
You were not always as you are now.
You were once a Man of Rohan.
Come down.
A Man of Rohan?
What is the house of Rohan...
but a thatched barn where brigands drink in the reek...
and their brats roll on the floor with the dogs?
The victory at Helm's Deep does not
belong to you, Theoden Horse-master.
You are a lesser son of greater sires.
Grima...
come down.
Be free of him.
- Free? He will never be free.
- No.
Get down, cur!
Saruman!
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
Tell us what you know!
You withdraw your guard, and I will
tell you where your doom will be decided.
I will not be held prisoner here.
Send word to all our allies...
and to every corner of
Middle-earth that still stands free.
The enemy moves against us. We
need to know where he will strike.
The filth of Saruman...
is washing away.
Trees will come back to live here.
Young trees.
- Wild trees.
- Pippin!
Bless my bark!
Peregrin Took!
I'll take that, my lad.
Quickly, now.
Tonight we remember those who gave
their blood to defend this country.
Hail the victorious dead.
Hail!
No pauses.
- No spills.
- And no regurgitation.
So it's a drinking game?
Last one standing wins.
What'll we drink to? Let's drink to victory!
To victory!
[Rohirric] Westu Aragorn hál.
[English] Be-thou Aragorn well!
I am happy for you.
He is an honorable man.
You are both honorable men.
It was not Theoden of Rohan
who led our people to victory.
Don't listen to me.
You are young.
And tonight is for you.
Here, here.
It's the Dwarves that go
swimming with little, hairy women.
I feel something.
A slight tingle in my fingers.
I think it's affecting me.
What did I say?
He can't hold his liquor.
Game over.
Oh, you can search far and wide
You can drink the whole town dry
But you'll never find a beer so brown
As the one we drink in our hometown
You can drink your fancy ales
You can drink them by the flagon
But the only brew for the brave and true
Pippin!
Comes from The Green Dragon
Thank you! I win!
No news of Frodo?
No word. Nothing.
We have time.
Every day, Frodo moves closer to Mordor.
Do we know that?
What does your heart tell you?
That Frodo is alive.
Yes.
Yes, he's alive.
Too risky. Too risky.
Thieves.
They stole it from us.
Kill them. Kill them. Kill them both.
Quiet! Mustn't wake them.
Mustn't ruin it now.
But they knows.
They knows.
They suspects us.
What's it saying, my precious, my love?
Is Smeagol losing his nerve?
No. Not.
Never. Smeagol hates nasty Hobbitses.
Smeagol wants to see them dead.
And we will.
Smeagol did it once. He can do it again.
It's ours!
Ours!
We must get the precious. We must get it back.
Patience! Patience, my love.
First we must lead them to her.
We lead them to the Winding Stair.
Yes, the stairs. And then?
Up, up, up, up, up the stairs we go...
until we come to the tunnel.
And when they go in...
there's no coming out.
She's always hungry.
She always needs to feed.
She must eat.
All she gets is filthy Orcses.
And they doesn't taste very nice, does they, precious?
No.
Not very nice at all, my love.
She hungers for sweeter meats.
Hobbit meat.
And when she throws away the
bones and the empty clothes...
then we will find it.
And take it for me!
For us.
Yes. We meant "for us."
Gollum. Gollum.
The precious will be ours...
once the Hobbitses are dead!
You treacherous little toad!
No! No! Master!
No, Sam! Leave him alone!
I heard it from his own mouth. He means to murder us.
Never! Smeagol wouldn't hurt a fly.
He's a horrid, fat Hobbit...
who hates Smeagol...
and who makes up nasty lies.
You miserable little maggot! I'll stove your head in!
Sam!
Call me a liar? You're a liar!
- You scare him off, we're lost!
- I don't care! I can't do it, Mr. Frodo.
- I won't wait around for him to kill us!
- I'm not sending him away.
You don't see it, do you?
He's a villain.
We can't do this by ourselves,
Sam. Not without a guide.
I need you on my side.
I'm on your side, Mr. Frodo.
I know, Sam. I know.
Trust me.
Come, Smeagol.
What time is it?
Not yet dawn.
I dreamed I saw a great wave...
climbing over green lands and above the hills.
I stood upon the brink.
It was utterly dark in the abyss before my feet.
A light shone behind me...
but I could not turn.
I could only stand there, waiting.
Night changes many thoughts.
Sleep, Eowyn.
Sleep...
while you can.
The stars are veiled.
Something stirs in the east.
A sleepless malice.
The Eye of the enemy is moving.
What are you doing?
Pippin!
Pippin?
Pippin.
- What, are you mad?
- I just want to look at it.
Just one more time.
Put it back.
Pippin.
No!
He is here.
I see you.
Pippin!
Help! Gandalf, help!
Someone help him!
Pippin!
Fool of a Took!
Look at me.
Gandalf, forgive me.
What did you see?
A tree.
There was a white tree...
in a courtyard of stone.
It was dead.
The city was burning.
Minas Tirith? Is that what you saw?
I saw...
I saw him.
I could hear his voice in my head.
And what did you tell him?
Speak!
He asked me my name. I didn't answer.
He hurt me.
What did you tell him about Frodo and the Ring?
There was no lie in Pippin's eyes.
A fool...
but an honest fool he remains.
He told Sauron nothing of Frodo and the Ring.
We've been strangely fortunate.
Pippin saw in the palantir a
glimpse of the enemy's plan.
Sauron moves to strike the city of Minas Tirith.
His defeat at Helm's Deep showed our enemy one thing.
He knows the heir of Elendil has come forth.
Men are not as weak as he supposed.
There is courage still, strength
enough perhaps to challenge him.
Sauron fears this.
He will not risk the peoples of
Middle-earth uniting under one banner.
He will raze Minas Tirith to the ground...
before he sees a king return to the throne of Men.
If the beacons of Gondor are
lit, Rohan must be ready for war.
Tell me...
why should we ride to the aid of
those who did not come to ours?
What do we owe Gondor?
- I will go.
- No!
- They must be warned.
- They will be.
You must come to Minas Tirith by another road.
Follow the river. Look to the black ships.
Understand this:
Things are now in motion that cannot be undone.
I ride for Minas Tirith...
and I won't be going alone.
Of all the inquisitive Hobbits,
Peregrin Took, you are the worst.
Hurry! Hurry!
Where are we going?
Why did you look?
Why do you always have to look?
- I don't know. I can't help it.
- You never can.
I'm sorry, all right?
- I won't do it again.
- Don't you understand?
The enemy thinks you have the Ring.
He's going to be looking for you,
Pip. They have to get you out of here.
And you...? You're coming with me?
Merry?
Come on.
How far is Minas Tirith?
Three days' ride, as the Nazgul flies.
And you better hope we don't
have one of those on our tail.
Here.
Something for the road.
The last of the Longbottom Leaf.
I know you've run out. You smoke too much, Pippin.
But... But we'll see each other soon.
- Won't we?
- I don't know.
I don't know what's going to happen.
- Merry.
- Run, Shadowfax.
Show us the meaning of haste.
Merry!
He's always followed me...
everywhere I went...
since before we were tweens.
I would get him into the worst sort of trouble...
but I was always there to get him out.
Now he's gone.
Just like Frodo and Sam.
One thing I have learned about Hobbits:
They're a most hardy folk.
Foolhardy, maybe. He's a Took.
Take her by the safest road.
A ship lies anchored in the Grey Havens.
It waits to carry her across the sea.
The last journey of Arwen Undomiel.
There is nothing for you here...
only death.
Lady Arwen...
we cannot delay.
My lady!
- Tell me what you have seen.
- Arwen.
You have the gift of foresight.
What did you see?
I looked into your future, and I saw death.
But there is also life.
You saw there was a child. You saw my son.
That future is almost gone.
But it is not lost.
Nothing is certain.
Some things are certain.
If I leave him now...
I will regret it forever.
It is time.
From the ashes a fire shall be woken
A light from the shadow shall spring
Renewed shall be blade that was broken
The crownless again shall be king
Re-forge the sword.
[Sindarin] Ada.
[English] Father.
Your hands are cold.
The life of the Eldar is leaving you.
This was my choice.
[Sindarin] Ada...
[English] Father...
Whether by your will or not...
there is no ship now that can bear me hence.
We've just passed into the realm of Gondor.
Minas Tirith.
City of kings.
Make way!
It's the tree.
Gandalf. Gandalf.
Yes, the White Tree of Gondor.
The tree of the king.
Lord Denethor, however, is not king.
He is a steward only, a caretaker of the throne.
Now listen carefully. Lord
Denethor is Boromir's father.
To give him news of his beloved
son's death would be most unwise.
And do not mention Frodo or the Ring.
And say nothing of Aragorn either.
In fact, it's better if you
don't speak at all, Peregrin Took.
Hail Denethor, son of Ecthelion,
lord and steward of Gondor.
I come with tidings in this
dark hour, and with counsel.
Perhaps you come to explain this.
Perhaps you come to tell me why my son is dead.
Boromir died to save us...
my kinsman and me.
- He fell defending us from many foes.
- Pippin.
I offer you my service, such as it is...
in payment of this debt.
This is my first command to you.
How did you escape and my son did not...
so mighty a man as he was?
The mightiest man may be slain by one arrow...
and Boromir was pierced by many.
Get up.
My lord, there will be a time to grieve for Boromir...
but it is not now.
War is coming.
The enemy is on your doorstep.
As steward, you are charged...
with the defense of this city.
Where are Gondor's armies?
You still have friends. You
are not alone in this fight.
Send word to Theoden of Rohan. Light the beacons.
You think you are wise, Mithrandir.
Yet for all your subtleties, you have not wisdom.
Do you think the eyes of the White Tower are blind?
I have seen more than you know.
With your left hand you would
use me as a shield against Mordor.
And with your right you'd seek to supplant me.
I know who rides with Theoden of Rohan.
Oh, yes. Word has reached my ears
of this Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
And I tell you now, I will not bow
to this Ranger from the North...
last of a ragged house long bereft of lordship.
Authority is not given to you to
deny the return of the king, steward.
The rule of Gondor is mine and no other's.
Come.
All has turned to vain ambition.
He would even use his grief as a cloak.
A thousand years this city has stood.
Now, at the whim of a madman, it will fall.
And the White Tree, the tree of the king...
will never bloom again.
- Why are they still guarding it?
- They guard it because they have hope.
A faint and fading hope that one day it will flower.
That a king will come and this
city will be as it once was...
before it fell into decay.
The old wisdom borne out of the West was forsaken.
Kings made tombs more splendid
than the houses of the living...
and counted the old names of their descent...
dearer than the names of their sons.
Childless lords sat in aged
halls, musing on heraldry...
or in high, cold towers, asking questions of the stars.
And so the people of Gondor fell into ruin.
The line of kings failed.
The White Tree withered.
The rule of Gondor was given over to lesser men.
Mordor.
Yes, there it lies.
This city has dwelt ever in the sight of its shadow.
A storm is coming.
This is not the weather of the world.
This is a device of Sauron's making.
A broil of fume he sends ahead of his host.
The Orcs of Mordor have no love of daylight...
so he covers the face of the sun...
to ease their passage along the road to war.
When the Shadow of Mordor reaches this city...
it will begin.
Well...
Minas Tirith...
very impressive.
- So where are we off to next?
- Oh, it's too late for that, Peregrin.
There's no leaving this city.
Help must come to us.
It must be getting near teatime.
Leastways, it would be in decent
places where there is still teatime.
We're not in decent places.
Mr. Frodo?
What is it?
It's just a feeling.
I don't think I'll be coming back.
Yes, you will. Of course you will.
That's just morbid thinking.
We're going there and back again...
just like Mr. Bilbo.
You'll see.
I think these lands were once
part of the kingdom of Gondor.
Long ago, when there was a king.
Mr. Frodo, look.
The king has got a crown again.
Come on, Hobbits! Mustn't stop now. This way.
So I imagine this is just a ceremonial position.
I mean, they don't actually
expect me to do any fighting.
- Do they?
- You're in the service of the steward now.
You'll have to do as you're told, Peregrin Took.
Ridiculous Hobbit.
Guard of the Citadel.
Thank you.
There's no more stars.
Is it time?
Yes.
It's so quiet.
It's the deep breath before the plunge.
I don't want to be in a battle...
but waiting on the edge of one
I can't escape is even worse.
Is there any hope, Gandalf, for Frodo and Sam?
There never was much hope.
Just a fool's hope.
Our enemy is ready.
His full strength's gathered.
Not only Orcs, but Men as well.
Legions of Haradrim from the south...
mercenaries from the coast.
All will answer Mordor's call.
Come on.
This will be the end of Gondor as we know it.
Here the hammer stroke will fall hardest.
If the river is taken, if the
garrison at Osgiliath falls...
the last defense of this city will be gone.
But we have the White Wizard.
That's got to count for something.
Gandalf?
Sauron has yet to reveal his deadliest servant...
the one who will lead Mordor's armies in war.
The one they say no living man can kill.
The Witch King of Angmar.
You've met him before.
He stabbed Frodo on Weathertop.
He is the lord of the Nazgul...
the greatest of the Nine.
Minas Morgul is his lair.
The Dead City.
Very nasty place. Full of enemies.
Quick. Quick.
They will see. They will see.
Come away. Come away. Look, we have found it.
The way into Mordor.
The secret stair.
Climb.
- No, Mr. Frodo!
- Not that way!
- What's it doing?
- No.
- They're calling me.
Hide! Hide!
I can feel his blade.
We come to it at last.
The great battle of our time.
Come away, Hobbits. We climb. We must climb.
The board is set.
The pieces are moving.
Up, up, up the stairs we go.
And then it's into the tunnel.
Hey, what's in this tunnel?
You listen to me, and you listen good and proper.
Anything happens to him, you have me to answer to.
One sniff something's not right...
one hair stands up on the back of my head, it's over.
No more slinker. No more stinker.
You're gone. Got it?
I'm watching you.
What was that about?
Nothing. Just clearing something up.
Peregrin Took, my lad, there is a task now to be done.
Another opportunity for one of the
Shire-folk to prove their great worth.
You must not fail me.
It's been very quiet across the river.
The Orcs are lying low.
The garrison may have moved out.
We've sent scouts to Cair Andros.
If the Orcs attack from the
north, we'll have some warning.
Quiet.
We need 10 more.
Kill him!
They're not coming from the north.
To the river. Quick. Quick. Go. Come on.
Faster.
Draw swords.
Hold! Hold them!
What?
Amon Din
The beacon. The beacon of Amon Din is lit.
Hope is kindled.
The beacons of Minas Tirith! The beacons are lit!
Gondor calls for aid.
And Rohan will answer.
Muster the Rohirrim.
Assemble the army at Dunharrow.
As many men as can be found. You have two days.
On the third, we ride for Gondor and war.
- Forward.
- Very good, sir.
- Gamling.
- My lord.
Make haste across the Riddermark.
Summon every able-bodied man to Dunharrow.
I will.
- Will you ride with us?
- Just to the encampment.
It's tradition for the women of
the court to farewell the men.
The men have found their captain.
They will follow you into battle, even to death.
You have given us hope.
Excuse me.
I have a sword.
Please accept it.
I offer you my service, Theoden King.
And gladly I accept it.
You shall be Meriadoc, esquire of Rohan.
Horse-Men.
I wish I could muster a legion of
Dwarves, fully armed and filthy.
Your kinsmen may have no need to ride to war.
I fear war already marches on their own lands.
So it is before the walls of Minas Tirith...
the doom of our time will be decided.
Now is the hour. Riders of Rohan, oaths you have taken.
Now, fulfill them all. To lord and land!
Faramir!
We can't hold them. The city is lost.
Tell the men to break cover. We ride for Minas Tirith.
Nazgul.
Take cover!
Nazgul!
Fall back. Fall back to Minas Tirith!
Fall back!
- Retreat! Retreat!
- Run for your lives!
The age of Men is over.
The time of the Orc has come.
- Keep going.
- It's the Nazgul.
Take cover, my lord!
It's coming!
- It's Mithrandir.
- The White Rider!
Pull!
Mithrandir.
They broke through our defenses.
They've taken the bridge and the west bank.
- Battalions of Orcs are crossing the river.
- It is as the Lord Denethor predicted.
- Long has he foreseen this doom.
- Foreseen and done nothing.
Faramir?
This is not the first Halfling
to have crossed your path.
No.
You've seen Frodo and Sam?
- Where? When?
- In Ithilien.
Not two days ago.
Gandalf, they're taking the road to the Morgul Vale.
And then the pass of Cirith Ungol.
What does that mean?
- What's wrong?
- Faramir, tell me everything.
Tell me all you know.
This is how you would serve your city?
You would risk its utter ruin?
I did what I judged to be right.
What you judged to be right.
You sent the Ring of Power into Mordor
in the hands of a witless Halfling.
It should have been brought back
to the Citadel to be kept safe.
Hidden.
Dark and deep in the vaults...
not to be used.
Unless at the uttermost end of need.
I would not use the Ring.
Not if Minas Tirith were falling
in ruin and I alone could save her.
Ever you desire to appear lordly and gracious...
as a king of old.
Boromir would have remembered his father's need.
He would have brought me a kingly gift.
Boromir would not have brought the Ring.
He would have stretched out his hand to
this thing and taken it. He would've fallen.
- You know nothing of this matter!
- He would have kept it for his own.
And when he returned...
you would not have known your son.
Boromir was loyal to me!
Not some wizard's pupil!
Father?
My son.
Leave me.
Careful, master. Careful.
Very far to fall.
Very dangerous are the stairs.
Come, master.
Come to Smeagol.
Mr. Frodo.
Get back, you!
Don't touch him!
Why does he hates poor Smeagol?
What has Smeagol ever done to him?
Master?
Master carries heavy burden.
Smeagol knows. Heavy, heavy burden.
Fat one cannot know.
Smeagol look after master.
He wants it.
He needs it. Smeagol sees it in his eye.
Very soon he will ask you for it. You will see.
The fat one will take it from you.
Send forth all legions.
Do not stop the attack until the city is taken.
Slay them all.
- What of the wizard?
- I will break him.
Where are Theoden's riders?
Will Rohan's army come?
Mithrandir.
Courage is the best defense that you have now.
What were you thinking, Peregrin Took?
What service can a Hobbit
offer such a great lord of Men?
It was well-done.
A generous deed should not
be checked with cold counsel.
You are to join the tower guard.
I didn't think they would find
any livery that would fit me.
Once belonged to a young boy of the city.
A very foolish one...
who wasted many hours slaying dragons
instead of attending to his studies.
- This was yours?
- Yes, it was mine.
My father had it made for me.
Well...
I'm taller than you were then.
Though I'm not likely to grow anymore, except sideways.
Never fitted me either.
Boromir was always the soldier.
They were so alike, he and my father.
Proud.
Stubborn even.
But strong.
I think you have strength of a different kind.
And one day your father will see it.
Here do I swear fealty and service to Gondor...
in peace or war...
in living or dying...
from...
From this hour henceforth...
until my lord release me...
or death take me.
And I shall not forget it...
nor fail to reward that which is given.
Fealty with love.
Valor with honor.
Disloyalty with vengeance.
I do not think we should so lightly
abandon the outer defenses...
defenses that your brother long held intact.
- What would you have me do?
- I will not yield...
the river in Pelennor unfought.
Osgiliath must be retaken.
My lord, Osgiliath is overrun.
Much must be risked in war.
Is there a captain here who still
has the courage to do his lord's will?
You wish now that our places had been exchanged...
that I had died and Boromir had lived.
Yes.
I wish that.
Since you were robbed of Boromir...
I will do what I can in his stead.
If I should return, think better of me, Father.
That will depend on the manner of your return.
What are you up to?
Sneaking off, are we?
Sneaking?
Fat Hobbit is always so polite.
Smeagol shows them secret ways
that nobody else could find...
and they say "sneak."
Sneak?
Very nice friend. Oh, yes, my precious.
- Very nice, very nice.
- All right. All right!
You just startled me is all.
What were you doing?
Sneaking.
Fine. Have it your own way.
I'm sorry to wake you, Mr. Frodo.
We have to be moving on.
It's dark still.
It's always dark here.
It's gone!
- The Elven bread.
- What?
That's all we have left.
He took it. He must have!
Smeagol? No, no, not poor Smeagol.
Smeagol hates nasty Elf bread.
You're a lying rat! What did you do with it?!
He doesn't eat it.
- He can't have taken it.
- Look.
What's this?
Crumbs on his jacketses. He took it!
He took it.
I seen him. He's always stuffing
his face when master's not looking.
That's a filthy lie!
You stinking, two-faced sneak!
- Sam!
- Call me...
Stop it!
Sam!
- I'll kill him!
- Sam! No!
Oh, my... I'm sorry. I didn't mean it
to go so far. I was just so... So angry.
Here, just... Let's
just rest a bit.
- I'm all right.
- No.
No, you're not all right. You're exhausted.
It's that Gollum.
It's this place.
It's that thing around your neck.
I could help a bit.
I could carry it for a while.
Carry it for a while.
I could carry it... I could carry it.
Share the load... Share the
load... the load... the load.
Get away!
I don't want to keep it.
I just want to help.
See? See?
He wants it for himself.
Shut up, you!
Go away! Get out of here!
No, Sam.
It's you.
I'm sorry, Sam.
But he's a liar.
He's poisoned you against me.
You can't help me anymore.
You don't mean that.
Go home.
Faramir!
Your father's will has turned to madness.
Do not throw away your life so rashly.
Where does my allegiance lie if not here?
This is the city of the Men of Numenor.
I will gladly give my life to defend her beauty...
her memory, her wisdom.
Your father loves you, Faramir.
He will remember it before the end.
Can you sing, Master Hobbit?
Well...
yes.
At least, well enough for my own people.
But we have no songs for great halls...
and evil times.
And why should your songs be unfit for my halls?
Come, sing me a song.
Home is behind
The world ahead
And there are many paths to tread
Through shadow
To the edge of night
Until the stars are all alight
Mist and shadow
Cloud and shade
All shall fade
All shall
Fade
March! March!
March! March! March!
Make way for the king.
Make way.
The king is here.
My lord.
Hail to you, sire.
Grimbold, how many?
I bring 500 men from the Westfold, my lord.
We have 300 more from Fenmarch, Theoden King.
- Where are the riders from Snowborn?
- None have come, my lord.
Six thousand spears.
Less than half of what I'd hoped for.
Six thousand will not be enough
to break the lines of Mordor.
More will come.
Every hour lost hastens Gondor's defeat.
We have till dawn, then we must ride.
The horses are restless...
and the men are quiet.
They grow nervous in the shadow of the mountain.
That road there...
where does that lead?
It is the road to the Dimholt,
the door under the mountain.
None who venture there ever return.
That mountain is evil.
Aragorn.
Let's find some food.
There.
A true esquire of Rohan.
I'm ready.
Sorry.
It isn't all that dangerous.
It's not even sharp.
Well, that's no good. You won't
kill many Orcs with a blunt blade.
Come on.
To the smithy. Go!
You should not encourage him.
You should not doubt him.
I do not doubt his heart, only the reach of his arm.
Why should Merry be left behind?
He has as much cause to go to war as you.
Why can he not fight for those he loves?
You know as little of war as that Hobbit.
When the fear takes him...
and the blood and the screams and
the horror of battle take hold...
do you think he would stand and fight?
He would flee.
And he would be right to do so.
War is the province of Men, Eowyn.
I choose a mortal life.
I wish I could've seen him...
one last time.
Sir?
King Theoden awaits you, my lord.
I take my leave.
My lord Elrond.
I come on behalf of one whom I love.
Arwen is dying.
She will not long survive the
evil that now spreads from Mordor.
The light of the Evenstar is failing.
As Sauron's power grows, her strength wanes.
Arwen's life is now tied to the fate of the Ring.
The Shadow is upon us, Aragorn.
The end has come.
It will not be our end, but his.
You ride to war, but not to victory.
Sauron's armies march on Minas Tirith, this you know.
But in secret he sends another force
which will attack from the river.
A fleet of Corsair ships sails from the south.
They'll be in the city in two days.
You're outnumbered, Aragorn.
You need more men.
There are none.
There are those who dwell in the mountain.
Murderers...
traitors.
You would call upon them to fight?
They believe in nothing.
They answer to no one.
They will answer to the king of Gondor.
Anduril, the Flame of the West,
forged from the shards of Narsil.
Sauron will not have forgotten the Sword of Elendil.
The blade that was broken shall return to Minas Tirith.
The man who can wield the power of this sword...
can summon to him an army more
deadly than any that walks this earth.
Put aside the Ranger.
Become who you were born to be.
Take the Dimholt road.
[Sindarin] Ónen i-Estel Edain.
[English] I gave hope to Men.
[Sindarin] Ú-chebin...
[English] I have kept...
[Sindarin] ...Estel anim.
[English] ...no hope for me.
Why are you doing this?
The war lies to the east. You
cannot leave on the eve of battle.
You cannot abandon the men.
Eowyn...
We need you here.
Why have you come?
Do you not know?
It is but a shadow and a thought that you love.
I cannot give you what you seek.
I have wished you joy since first I saw you.
Just where do you think you're off to?
Not this time.
This time you must stay, Gimli.
Have you learned nothing of
the stubbornness of Dwarves?
You might as well accept it.
We're going with you, laddie.
- What's happening?
- Where is he going?
Where's he going?
I don't understand.
Lord Aragorn!
Why does he leave on the eve of battle?
He leaves because there is no hope.
He leaves because he must.
Too few have come.
We cannot defeat the armies of Mordor.
No...
we cannot.
But we will meet them in battle nonetheless.
I have left instruction.
The people are to follow your rule in my stead.
Take up my seat in the Golden Hall.
Long may you defend Edoras...
if the battle goes ill.
What other duty would you have me do, my lord?
Duty?
No.
I would have you smile again...
not grieve for those whose time has come.
You shall live to see these days renewed...
and no more despair.
What kind of army would linger in such a place?
One that is cursed.
Long ago, the Men of the Mountains swore an oath...
to the last king of Gondor...
to come to his aid...
to fight.
But when the time came...
when Gondor's need was dire...
they fled...
vanishing into the darkness of the mountain.
And so Isildur cursed them...
never to rest until they had fulfilled their pledge.
Who shall call them from the grey twilight?
The forgotten people.
The heir of him to whom the oath they swore.
From the north shall he come.
Need shall drive him.
He shall pass the door to the Paths of the Dead.
The very warmth of my blood seems stolen away.
The way is shut.
It was made by those who are dead.
And the Dead keep it.
The way is shut.
Brego!
I do not fear death.
Well, this is a thing unheard-of.
An Elf will go underground where a Dwarf dare not?
Oh.
Oh, I'd never hear the end of it.
We must ride light and swift.
It is a long road ahead.
And man and beast must reach the
end with the strength to fight.
Little Hobbits do not belong in war, Master Meriadoc.
All my friends have gone to battle.
I would be ashamed to be left behind.
It is a three-day gallop to Minas Tirith.
And none of my riders can bear you as a burden.
I want to fight.
I will say no more.
Ride with me.
My lady.
Form up! Move out!
Ride!
Ride now to Gondor!
[Black Speech]  Katmuda!
[English]  Death to men!
[Black Speech]  Gorosh!
[English]  Louder!
[Black Speech]  Katmuda!
[English]  Death to men!
[Black Speech]  Gorosh!
[English]  Louder!
[Black Speech]  Katmuda!
[English]  Death to men!
[Black Speech]  Gorosh chadar!
[English]  Loud enough!
What is it?
What do you see?
I see shapes of men.
And of horses.
Where?
Pale banners like shreds of cloud.
Spears rise...
like winter-thickets through a shroud of mist.
The Dead are following.
They have been summoned.
The Dead?
Summoned?
I knew that.
Very good.
Very good! Legolas!
Do not look down.
Who enters my domain?
One who will have your allegiance.
The Dead do not suffer the living to pass.
You will suffer me.
The way is shut.
It was made by those who are dead.
And the Dead keep it.
The way is shut.
Now you must die.
I summon you to fulfill your oath.
None but the king of Gondor may command me.
That line was broken.
It has been remade.
Fight for us...
and regain your honor.
What say you?
You waste your time, Aragorn.
They had no honor in life, they have none now in death.
I am Isildur's heir.
Fight for me...
and I will hold your oaths fulfilled.
What say you?
You have my word!
Fight, and I will release you from this living death!
What say you?!
Stand, you traitors!
Out!
Legolas!
Run!
We fight.
Open the gate! Quick!
Quick! Hurry!
Faramir!
Say not that he has fallen.
They were outnumbered.
None survived.
Fear.
The city is rank with it.
Let us ease their pain.
Release the prisoners.
Catapults!
My sons are spent.
My line has ended.
He's alive!
The House of Stewards has failed.
He needs medicine, my lord.
My line has ended!
My lord!
Rohan...
has deserted us.
Theoden's betrayed me.
Abandon your posts!
Flee! Flee for your lives!
Prepare for battle!
Hurry, men! To the wall! Defend the wall!
Over here!
Return to your posts!
Send these foul beasts into the abyss.
Stay where you are.
We need more rubble!
Watch out!
Down to the lower levels. Quick!
Double up, men!
Hold them back! Do not give in to fear.
Stand to your posts! Fight!
Not at the towers!
Aim for the trolls! Kill the trolls!
Bring them down!
Fight them back!
Peregrin Took!
- Go back to the Citadel!
- They'd called us out to fight.
This is no place for a Hobbit.
Guard of the Citadel, indeed.
Now, back, up the hill. Quickly. Quick!
What are you doing, you useless scum?!
The door won't give. It's too strong.
Get back there and smash it down.
But nothing can breach it.
Grond will breach it.
Bring up the wolf's head.
Grond! Grond! Grond! Grond!
Grond! Grond! Grond!
Grond! Grond! Grond!!